Register of the Bertram David Wolfe papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Incremental Materials - Photographs, 1890-1999 (Boxes 173-176)
  - Wolfe, Ella and Frida Kahlo, 1933 (Folder 173: 9)
  - Wolfe, Ella and American students, Saltillo, Mexico, 1948 (Folder 173: 10)
  - Wolfe, Ella, 1960-1979 (Folder 173: 11)
  - Wolfe, Ella, 1980-1990 (Folder 173: 12)
  - Wolfe, Ella and Mario Balibrera, 1994 (Folder 173: 13)
  - Wolfe, Ella, 1994-1999 (Folder 173: 14)
  - Wolfe, Henry and Paul, 1920 (Folder 173: 15)
  - Wolfe, Lillian, 1920 (Folder 173: 16)
  - Aunt of Bertram Wolfe, 1890 (Folder 173: 17)
  - Goldberg, Harry, 1920-1955 (Folder 173: 18)
  - Goldberg, Harry and Rose, 1953 (Folder 173: 19)
  - Goldberg, Barnet, 1920 (Folder 173: 20)
  - Schwarz, Sasha, 1910 (Folder 173: 21)
  - Pestkovski, Stanislas, 1924 (Folder 173: 22)
  - Lovestone, Jay, 1920-1940 (Folder 173: 23)
  - Lovestone, Jay and Harry Goldberg, 1956 (Folder 173: 24)
  - Rivera, Diego, 1915-1940 (Folder 173: 25)
  - Rivera, Diego and Frida Kahlo, 1935 (Folder 173: 26)
  - Rivera, Diego and José Clemente Orozco, 1945 (Folder 173: 27)
  - Rivera, Diego and Emma Hurtado, 1955 (Folder 173: 28)
  - Kahlo, Frida, 1930-1935 (Folder 173: 29)
  - Marin, Guadalupe, 1925 (Folder 173: 30)
  - Rivera, Marika, 1950 (Folder 173: 31)
  - Orozco, José Clemente, 1945 (Folder 173: 32)
  - Kollontai, Alexandra, 1928 (Folder 173: 33)
  - Felipe, León, 1923 (Folder 173: 34)
  - Haykiss, León, 1925 (Folder 173: 35)
  - Bardas, Nicolás, 1921 (Folder 173: 36)
  - Hurtado, Emma, 1940 (Folder 173: 37)
  - Gumperz, Julian, 1940-1960 (Folder 173: 38)
  - Gupta, Heramba L., 1918 (Folder 173: 39)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1970 (Folder 173: 40)
  - Bolloten, Burnett and Betty, 1960-1983 (Folder 173: 41)
  - Kazin, Alfred, 1960 (Folder 173: 42)
  - Haya de la Torre, Víctor Raúl, 1925 (Folder 173: 43)
  - Felipe, Salud, 1931 (Folder 173: 44)
  - Evans, Ernestine, 1925 (Folder 173: 45)
  - Goldstein, Darra and family, 1985-1996 (Folder 173: 46)
  - Rozek, Edward, 1972-1981 (Folder 173: 47)
  - Lasky, Mel, 1960 (Folder 173: 48)
  - Schapiro, Leonard, 1980 (Folder 173: 49)
  - Maurin, Mario, Elana, and Jeanne, 1989 (Folder 173: 50)
  - Teller, Edward, 1979 (Folder 173: 51)
  - Shattan, Joseph and family, 1988-1997 (Folder 173: 52)
  - Goldstein, Helen and Irving, 1984 (Folder 174: 1)
  - Jolis, Bert and family, 1962 (Folder 174: 2)
  - Jolis, James, 1974 (Folder 174: 3)
  - Morgan, Ted, 1970 (Folder 174: 4)
  - Hayakawa, S. I., 1972 (Folder 174: 5)
  - Lloyd-Jones, Hugh, 1976 (Folder 174: 6)
  - Cullen, Greg, 1990 (Folder 174: 7)
  - Kukk, Hilja, 1995 (Folder 174: 8)
  - Graves, Anna, 1930 (Folder 174: 9)
  - Gorkin, Rita and Julian, 1960 (Folder 174: 10)
  - Allilueva, Svetlana and Olga Peters, 1977 (Folder 174: 11)
  - Peters, Olga, 1972-1975 (Folder 174: 12)
  - Balibrera, Mario and family, 1994 (Folder 174: 13-14)
  - Scenes in Spain and Portugal photographed by Mario Balibrera, 1994 (Folder 174: 15-16)
  - Scenes in Portugal photographed by Mario Balibrera, 1998 (Folder 174: 17)
  - Scenes in Spain photographed by Mario Balibrera, 1999 (Folder 174: 18)
  - Scenes in New Mexico photographed by Mario Balibrera, 1999 (Folder 174: 19)
  - Scenes in Seattle, Washington, photographed by Mario Balibrera, 1999 (Folder 174: 20)
  - Shostakovich, Dmitri, 1950 (Folder 174: 21)
  - Dzerzhinsky, Felix, 1920 (Folder 174: 22)
  - Stalin, Joseph, 1910-1950 (Folder 174: 23)
  - Stalin, Joseph, Franklin Roosevelt, and Winston Churchill at the Teheran Conference, 1943 (Folder 174: 24)
  - Stalin, Joseph and Sergei Kirov, 1935 (Folder 174: 25)
  - Trotsky, Leon, 1917-1940 (Folder 174: 26)
  - Trotsky, Leon and Leon Sedov, 1935 (Folder 174: 27)
  - Trotsky, Leon and Cristina Kahlo, 1937 (Folder 174: 28)
  - Kerensky, Alexander and members of the State Duma Committee, 1917 (Folder 174: 29)
  - Roy, Manabendra Nath, 1950 (Folder 174: 30)
  - Conference of the Mexican Communist Party, 1920 (Folder 174: 31)
  - Rally of the Mexican Communist Party, 1924 (Folder 174: 32)
  - Members of the Liga Anti-imperialista, 1924 (Folder 174: 33)
  - Chinese parade with posters of Joseph Stalin, 1950 (Folder 174: 34)
  - Artworks by Diego Rivera, 1930-1950 (Folder 175: 1-14)
  - Artworks by Diego Rivera, 1930-1950 (Folder 176: 1-10)
  - Paintings by Frida Kahlo, 1930-1940 (Folder 176: 11)
- Incremental Materials - Oversize Materials, 1905-1985 (Box 177)
  Contains awards and diplomas, artwork, photographs, and maps, arranged by physical form.
  - Awards and diplomas, 1909-1975
    - Bertram Wolfe, 1909-1975
      - Diploma, elementary education, New York City, 1909 (Box-folder 177: 1)
      - Diplomas, Brooklyn Boys High School, 1912
      - Bachelor of Arts diploma and certificate, College of the City of New York, 1916
        Includes honorary degree (with stamp) from La Universidad Nacional de Mexico, Visa, 1923.
      - Medals for academic proficiency, College of the City of New York, 1916 (Box 177)
      - Master of Arts diploma, Columbia University, 1931
      - Doctor of Laws diploma, University of California at Davis, 1962 (Box-folder 177: 2)
      - Certificate of award, Townsend Harris Medal, 1964
      - Certificates of fellowship, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1975
    - Ella Wolfe, 1923-1931
      - Bachelor of Arts diploma, Hunter College, 1918 (Box 177)
      - Master of Arts diploma, Columbia University, 1931
  - Artwork, 1931-1980 (Box-folder 177: 3)
    - Print of a drawing of Vladimir I. Lenin by N. A. Andreyev, undated
    - Watercolor by Marika Rivera, 1931
    - Detail of Diego Rivera mural depicting Bertram Wolfe, 1933
    - Drawing of Clara Zetkin, 1980
    - Drawing of Vladimir I. Lenin, 1980
  - Photographs, 1905-1985 (Box-folder 177: 4-5)
    - Luxemburg, Rosa, 1905
    - Wolfe, Bertram and Spanish Civil War veterans, 1939
    - Wolfe, Bertram and others posed in front of mural, San Francisco, 1940
    - Wolfe, Bertram, 1960
    - Goldberg, Harry, 1960
    - Balabanoff, Angelica, 1960
    - View of Almeria, Spain, 1985
  - Maps, 1951 (Box-folder 177: 6)
    - "U.S.S.R.-Caucus Area Administrative Divisions, 1950,", 1951
    - "Caucasia - Historical Names,", 1951
- Incremental Materials - Printed Matter, 1907-1986 (Boxes 178-182)
  Contains books by Bertram D. Wolfe, other monographs, and serial issues, arranged in three groups, then by title.
  - Books by Bertram Wolfe, 1934-1986
    - Portrait of America (with Diego Rivera), 1934 (Folder 178: 1)
    - Civil War in Spain, 1937 (Folder 178: 2-4)
    - Portrait of Mexico (with Diego Rivera), 1937 (Folder 178: 5-7)
    - Keep America out of War (with Norman Thomas), 1939 (Folder 178: 5)
    - Diego Rivera: His Life and Times, 1939 (Folder 179: 1)
    - Deathless Days, 1940 (Folder 179: 2)
    - Mundo sin muerte, 1942 (Folder 179: 3)
    - Compilation of scripts prepared by Bertram Wolfe for the Voice of America, 1951-1954 (Folder 179: 4)
    - 3 Männer, die die Welt erschütterten, 1951 (Folder 180: 1)
    - I tre artefici della rivoluzione d'ottobre, 1953 (Folder 180: 2)
    - Tres que hicieron una revolución, 1956 (Folder 180: 3)
    - I successori di Stalin, 1957 (Folder 180: 4)
    - Marxismo, 1967 (Folder 180: 5)
    - The Bridge and the Abyss, 1967 (Folder 180: 6)
    - Marx und die Marxisten, 1968 (Folder 181: 1)
    - Brücke und Abgrund, 1970 (Folder 181: 2)
    - La fabulosa vida de Diego Rivera, 1986 (Folder 181: 3)
  - Other monographs, 1907-1920
    - Poetical Works of Alfred Lord Tennyson, inscribed by Bertram Wolfe to Ella Wolfe, 1907 (Folder 181: 4)
    - The Little Book of Modern Verse, inscribed by Bertram Wolfe to Ella Wolfe, 1913 (Folder 181: 5)
    - Trotsky, Leon, Our Revolution, with marginal notes by Bertram Wolfe, 1918 (Folder 181: 6)
    - Revolutionary Radicalism, Its History, Purpose and Tactics, 1920 (Folder 181: 7-8)
      Report by Senate of the State of New York in which Bertram Wolfe is mentioned.
  - Serial issues, 1937-1938
    - Marxist Quarterly, vol. I, nos. 1-3, 1937 (Folder 182: 1)
    - The New International, 1938 February-May, July, October, and December (Folder 182: 2)
- CLOSED (Box 183)
  Use copies available in box 12.
- Previously Separated Materials, 1948-1976 (Box 184)
  Materials relating to the Hoover Institution that were separated from the rest of the collection, as well as a speech clearance form that had been stored with the collection's sound recordings.
  - Biographical file - reports on activities, Hoover Institution, 1967-1975 (Box-folder 184: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1976
    - Belmont, Alan, 1966-1975 (Box-folder 184: 2)
    - Benson, Brien, 1968-1973 (Box-folder 184: 3)
    - Campbell, Rita, 1966, 1969 (Box-folder 184: 4)
    - Campbell, W. Glenn, 1960-1976 (Box-folder 184: 5)
    - Coors, Joseph (Adolph Coors Company), 1972 (Box-folder 184: 6)
    - Drachkovitch, Milorad, 1957-1974 (Box-folder 184: 7)
    - Freeman, Roger, 1970 (Box-folder 184: 8)
    - Hobson, James (Jim), 1966-1972 (Box-folder 184: 9)
    - Hoover Institution, 1948-1949, 1965-1976 (Box-folder 184: 10)
    - Lassner, Franz, 1970 (Box-folder 184: 11)
    - Staar, Richard, 1968-1976 (Box-folder 184: 12)
    - Sworakowski, Witold, 1950, 1963-1968 (Box-folder 184: 13)
  - Speeches and writings - Stanford University speech clearance form, 1969 (Box-folder 184: 14)
    Form signed by Bertram Wolfe granting Stanford University's radio station KZSU permission to record and broadcast his "The Extraordinary Adventures of a Yankee in Mexico" speech of 9 May 1969, as well as make a tape recording of the speech available to other organizations. Also includes a KZSU tape identification slip.
  - Subject file - Hoover Institution, 1969, undated (Box-folder 184: 15)
    Consists of guidelines on reimbursement for travel and a blank questionnaire.
- 2015 Incremental Materials - Biographical File, 1948-2000 (Box 185)
  - Awards and achievements, 1962, 1964, undated (Box-folder 185: 1)
  - Biographical data, undated (Box-folder 185: 2)
  - Clippings, 1948-2000 (Box-folder 185: 3)
    Articles relating to Bertram Wolfe, including book reviews and obituaries. Also includes a photocopy of the obituary of Ella Wolfe.
  - Conference materials, circa 1967, 1970, 1973 (Box-folder 185: 4)
  - Lecture announcements, undated (Box-folder 185: 5)
    See also: Clippings.
  - Memorial tributes, circa 1977, 1985 (Box-folder 185: 6)
- 2015 Incremental Materials - Correspondence, 1911-1998 (Box 185)
  Copies and originals, mostly of correspondence sent by Bertram and Ella Wolfe, arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Includes some enclosures, such as newspaper clippings.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies (Joseph S. Berliner), 1972 (Box-folder 185: 7)
    Includes photostat of Award for Distinguished Contributions to Slavic Studies that Wolfe received on 17 March 1972.
  - American Psychoanalytic Association, 1971 (Box-folder 185: 8)
  - Bettelheim, Bruno, 1971 (Box-folder 185: 9)
  - Buckley, William F., Jr., 1971 (Box-folder 185: 10)
  - Busbey, Fred E., 1953 (Box-folder 185: 11)
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1973 (Box-folder 185: 12)
  - Staar, Richard, 1971 (Box-folder 185: 13)
    A letter from Haven Webb, a State Department official, to Dr. Staar, referencing Wolfe's An Ideology in Power.
  - Voice of America (Leonard F. Erikson), 1954 (Box-folder 185: 14)
    Includes text of press release announcing Wolfe's resignation as Chief of the Ideological Advisory Staff.
  - Wolfe, 1911-1972 (Box-folder 185: 15)
    Includes letters addressed generally to members of the Wolfe family (usually both of Bertram Wolfe's brothers, Paul and Henry).
  - Wolfe, Evelyn (Rinna), 1957-1998 (Box-folder 185: 16)
    Mostly letters sent by Bertram Wolfe to Evelyn (Rinna), though there are a couple later letters to her from others.
  - Wolfe, Henry, 1925-1978 (Box-folder 185: 17)
  - Wolfe, Lillian, 1924-1925 (Box-folder 185: 18)
  - Wolfe, Paul, 1924-1973 (Box-folder 185: 19)
  - Wolfe, Rachel, 1920s? (Box-folder 185: 20)
- 2015 Incremental Materials - Speeches and Writings, 1934-1970 (Boxes 185-186)
  - "The Government of Doctor Caligari,", undated (Box-folder 185: 21)
  - "In Place of an Introduction,", undated (Box-folder 185: 22)
  - "León Felipe, Poet of Spain's Exodus and Tears,", undated (Box-folder 185: 23)
  - What Is the Communist Opposition?, undated (Box-folder 186: 1)
  - Marx and America, pamphlet, 1934 (Box-folder 186: 2)
  - "Politics and Fiction in Mexico," American Mercury, 1948 June (Box-folder 186: 3)
  - "An Exclusive Radio Interview with Stalin on Peace and War," three part Voice of America radio broadcast, 1951 October (Box-folder 186: 4)
    Transcript booklet. Planned and written by Wolfe.
  - Voice of America, Ideological Special scripts, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 186: 5)
  - "Drowning in a Paper Sea," New Leader, 1954 May 3 (Box-folder 186: 6)
  - "The Conversion of a Communist," New Leader, 1954 June 7 (Box-folder 186: 7)
  - "Lenin on World War I," New Leader, 1955 March 14 (Box-folder 186: 8)
  - "Is Co-existence Possible?," Tamiment Institute Public Forum (with others), Museum of Modern Art, New York, 1955 April 14 (Box-folder 186: 9)
  - "The 'New' Soviety Leaders," New Leader, 1956 January 23 (Box-folder 186: 10)
  - Review in New Leader of George F. Kennan, Russia, the Atom and the West, 1958 May 19 (Box-folder 186: 11)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of General Baron Peter N. Wrangel, Always With Honour, 1958 June 15 (Box-folder 186: 12)
  - "U.S. Policy and Communist Vulnerability," New Leader, 1959 September 7 (Box-folder 186: 13)
  - "Mr. K's Favorite Reporter," New York Times Magazine, 1960 June 5 (Box-folder 186: 14)
  - "The New Gospel According to Khrushchev," Foreign Affairs, reprint, 1960 July (Box-folder 186: 15)
  - "Rosa Luxemburg and V. I. Lenin: The Opposite Poles of Revolutionary Socialism," Antioch Review, reprint, 1961 Summer (Box-folder 186: 16)
  - "Leon Trotsky as Historian," Slavic Review, reprint, 1961 October (Box-folder 186: 17)
  - "Graduating Into the Second Half of the Twentieth Century," commencement address, Sacramento State College, 1962 June 8 (Box-folder 186: 18)
  - "Communist Ideology and Soviet Foreign Policy," Foreign Affairs, reprint, 1962 October (Box-folder 186: 19)
  - "French Socialism, German Theory, and the Flaw in the Foundation of the Socialist Internationals," Essays in Russian and Soviety History in Honor of Geroid Tanquary Robinson, reprint, 1963 (Box-folder 186: 20)
  - "Lenin and Inessa Armand," Slavic Review, reprint, 1963 March (Box-folder 186: 21)
  - "Angelic Balabanoff and V. I. Lenin: The Opposing Poles of the Socialist Movement Against War," Antioch Review, reprint, 1964 Summer (Box-folder 186: 22)
  - "Leninism," chapter in Marxism in the Modern World, edited by Milorad M. Drachkovitch, 1965 (Box-folder 186: 23)
  - "Some Reflections on the Convergence Theory," Western Politica, 1966 Autumn (Box-folder 186: 24)
  - " Das Kapital One Hundred Years Later," Antioch Review, reprint, 1966-1967 Winter (Box-folder 186: 25)
  - Review in Chicago Daily News of Svetlana Alliluyeva, Twenty Letters to a Friend, 1967 September 23 (Box-folder 186: 26)
  - Table of contents, An Ideology in Power: Reflections on the Russian Revolution, circa 1968 (Box-folder 186: 27)
  - Letter to the editor, Russian Review, 1969 July (Box-folder 186: 28)
  - "Dress Rehearsals for the Great Terror," Studies in Comparative Communism, reprint, 1970 April (Box-folder 186: 29)
- 2015 Incremental Materials - Photographs, undated (Box-folder 186: 30)
  Photographs of Bertram Wolfe at various stages of his life and two photographs of an unidentified woman.
- 2015 Incremental Materials - Printed Matter, 1971-1996, undated (Box 186)
  - Clippings, 1971, 1982, 1984, circa 1996 (Box-folder 186: 31)
    Consists of a review of Joseph P. Lash, Eleanor and Franklin: The Story of Their Relationship Based on Eleanor Roosevelt's Private Papers; an article on the World Psychiatric Association and its reaction to the use of psychiatry for political repression; an article about the discovery of a newspaper story Ernest Hemingway wrote on the Spanish Civil War; an article on Diego Rivera and cubism; and an article on the 50th anniversary of the massacre of Jews in Kielce, Poland.
  - Maps, undated (Box-folder 186: 32)
    Consists of a Special Edition Global News Map, a News Map of the Changing World, and a United Press War Map.
  - Pamphlets, undated (Box-folder 186: 33)
    Consists of a reprint of The Declaration of Independence and information on the Hoover Institution.
- 2015 Incremental Materials - Subject File, 1932-1976 (Box 187)
  Annotated clippings and printed matter, notes, and correspondence relating to "apologetics/apologists for Communism and the USSR."
- 2017 Release of Declassified Government Records, 1950-1959